A Guide to the Charles W. Wampler, Jr. Collection 1798-1962
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Charles W. Wampler, Jr. Collection 1798-1962
Special Collections, James Madison University
3095
This collection comprises five folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Charles W. Wampler, Jr. in March, 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Wamplers have been one of the most influential families in Rockingham County, VA. John Wampler and family, members of the Brethren Church, moved from Pennsylvania to the Timberville area of the county in 1811. In 1871, John Wampler III purchased a farm in Dayton that he named Sunny Slope and built a house there. His son, Charles W., began various agricultural experiments, particularly in poultry raising, and was one of the earliest farmers to hatch eggs in incubators. He served as the first Rockingham County Extension Agent and in 1927, with two brothers, founded the Wampler Feed and Seed Company. His son Charles Jr., born at Sunny Slope in 1915, continued and furthered these business ventures and community endeavors, including serving in the VA House of Delegates from 1954-1966.
Scope and Content
This collection contains letters, deeds, and agricultural information from 1798 to 1962 related to the Wampler family of Dayton, VA.
Arrangement
Family papers, Land surveys and management, Legal documents, Financial documents, Agricultural information
Wampler, Charles W. "My Grandfather, my grandchildren and me; an autobiography." Harrisonburg, VA; Dayton, VA: Shenandoah Press, 1968. Available in the Brethren Room of Bridgewater College Library (call no. 926.3 W243m 1968).
Contents List
- Family Papers 1854-1971 and undated, 16 items and 2 envelopes (Folder 1)
  Mostly letters on agriculture, family and church matters, and an 1871-1971 Wampler Family Reunion booklet.
- Land Surveys and measurements 1838-1882 and undated, 5 surveys and 1 list of measurements (Folder 2)
- Legal Documents 1798 (typed transcript of original)-1962, 35 items (Folder 3)
  Mostly tax receipts and deeds involving the Wampler family, but also:
  - Patent 1844
    patent describing an improved Wheat Fan invented by David Watkins of Port Republic, with receipt for purchase by John Wampler of exclusive rights to use it.
  - Will 1861
    Will of John Wampler, with 1863 codicil.
- Financial Documents 1858-1930 and undated, 52 items (Folder 4)
  Mostly promises to pay, receipts for miscellaneous purchases, and receipts for inheritance monies received, but also:
  - Stock Certificate 1859
    Stock certificate for Mt. Jackson and Howard's Lick Turnpike Co.
  - Receipt of Sale 1872
    Sale of right to use Cray's Washing Machine.
  - Letterhead receipts 1927, 1930
    Letterhead receipts for sales by Wampler Feed & Seed Co.
  - Receipt of payments 1888, 1889, 1901
    Receipts for payment of yearly toll on Warm Springs and Harrisonburg Turnpike.
- Agricultural Information 1895-1959 and undated, 14 items (Folder 5)
  Lists of books, three photos, 1959 Yearbook of Agriculture with many inserts and notes, and information sheets and brochures, mostly concerning poultry. Includes several brochures produced by Wampler's Feed & Seed Co. describing the poultry business, and a photocopy of Wampler's Practical Turkey Methods, Harrisonburg, VA, 1929.